hey everyone welcome back to this Tosca
playlist and we are going to continue
with our API testing Series so this is
the part 3 of this series and if you
have not watched the earlier parts then
go ahead and watch it uh on our Channel
so now that uh we have scanned our URI
and all the different messages the
structure and functions of the API are
already created for us uh in our API
scan
so now we are going to take the next
step which is to uh create test cases
from this particular messages right so
that will do in Tosca commander and for
this particular session I have created
uh or I have opened the Tosca API scan
from the commander okay so I haven't
opened it uh from the Standalone version
I've opened it from the Tosca Commander
okay
so for this purpose I'm going to use
three different messages okay API
messages and these are the first is post
okay and this was basically uh it will
add a new pet to this pet store okay and
I have changed the name here to Max okay
and the remaining uh payload is still
the same
and then um we are going to use the get
pet by ID okay and this uh we need to
pass a pet ID you can see here it's uh
path parameter so I have provided a
value here okay
and then uh in delete
um I'm going to provide a API key and a
pet ID okay so this is going to delete
this particular pet which was created
earlier okay so basically three API
messages or request uh first will uh is
a post request which will add a new pet
into the pet store and then the get bed
ID which is a get request which will get
the information uh from the pet store of
this pet new pet uh using the ID and
then we'll finally delete uh the new pet
which was created on the pet store okay
so these three API requests will be
using okay
now I've already tested and these are
working fine but what we want to do is
uh we want to create our test cases so
that we can verify some of the values
here right and to do this as I said
earlier we have to basically export our
API test case okay and how we can do
that is uh we have to actually
select the individual messages okay so
don't forget this otherwise it will only
export the single request which is
selected or message which is selected at
the present you have to select all the
messages which you want to export okay
also what we have to do is we have to
create a separate component folder for
this otherwise it is going to create
this or export this into the root folder
which is not ideal okay
so let's create a component folder and
I'm going to name it API testing
okay inside this API testing and you
have to make sure that it is selected
before you export your API messages
so once it is selected okay go ahead and
go to API test case and go to export
okay now uh Tosca is exporting all these
messages and it will automatically
create the required folders and the
required structure for these API
messages okay so let's go back to Tosca
commander and now you can see under this
component folder we have got this
modules okay
now surprisingly you will see that we
had got three messages but now we have
got six modules okay so don't get
confused uh the reason for this is for
each message okay
uh Tosca has created one request type
and one response type okay so for post
we have a request and response for
delete we have a request in response and
forget we have a request and response
okay because we'll be sending a request
and we'll be receiving a response okay
and similarly we have got a test cases
folder okay and here also under each
message you will see that we have got
two requests or two
um the steps which is one is post and
one is request and one is response okay
so Tosca creates everything for you uh
the module the structure the test cases
okay and the request and response okay
everything is created but after this we
have to make some configuration changes
and also we need to put some
verifications so that we can execute
these test cases okay
foreign
you can always rename this modules
um as per your application it's always
recommended
but um what we have to see is now inside
this API modules okay there is an extra
tab called technical view this is not
available when you scan your other
applications but it is available when
you scan your apis okay and this is the
exact view which was present in the API
scan window okay so it has got all the
information for the API message the
endpoint the method the resource okay
the Header information the payload
now let's see how we can execute this
API request right from our test cases
without even going to API scan right
since we have now captured everything
under modules which is present in the
technical view we can directly go ahead
and execute this test cases okay so for
example if I execute this post request
and response to add a pet
so it will execute fine right but in the
log you won't be able to see much
because we haven't captured anything
right so there are no verifications and
we are also not capturing the status
code uh it is only displaying the server
response time which is not very useful
right so if you want to test a API uh we
should be verifying um at least the
status code which is returned by the
response right and for that we need to
add some attributes to this module
so in the API modules these attributes
are nothing but uh the elements of the
payload or the status code or the
response time or the parameters right so
whatever is contained inside the API
message we can add them as module
attributes and these are also known as
business parameters because then you can
change these values in your test cases
okay so for example if I want to verify
this post request right and I want to
verify the status code so what I can do
I can select the status code and I can
click on ADD at the top of the API
testing tab okay so this is going to add
a module attribute or business parameter
for status code okay similarly I can add
all of these payload items into this
particular module attributes as module
attributes right so if I select
everything and click on ADD then it is
going to add all the different
attributes into this module
okay and once we add that it will also
get reflected in our test case okay so
if I go back to my test case now you can
see under the test step I can see an
additional uh test right the step which
is for status code
and also I can pass a value here okay so
there are two ways to do that there will
be the default value which is captured
by the scan okay and you can see all the
values are already here which has been
captured so we can select any of these
values so I'm going to select 200 okay
because that's what it should return and
then I'm going to select the action mode
verify okay
so this is one of the verification you
can do on your particular request okay
now if I go ahead and run this again
so this time around in the log info you
can see that the status code
verification was successful and it will
show you the expected and actual value
so this is the actual testing of your
API right now you are actually testing
the API because you are checking
something you are verifying something
and you have to make sure that these
verifications are at least there for
every post or any get request right so
at least the status code should be
verified
now let's try to verify some more things
on this particular post request because
uh when it Returns the response it is
also returning us the payload right and
that will contain a certain Elements
which you want to verify uh when we send
this particular request so let's go back
to our response and here you will see uh
what we want to verify as maybe the name
right and maybe the ID which will be
using later on but right now we we may
not be verifying this particular ID okay
but
um let's go ahead and verify this name
which we are sending okay so uh what
we'll do is we will add this particular
name as a business parameter here okay
and what I'm also going to do is I'm
going to also add this okay name uh into
this particular request
and that's because uh you can see the
name is little different here I changed
it here but I did not run this before I
scanned this particular API okay so
that's why it has captured the name from
my previous run but right now we can we
can do that we can change that okay
so I've added the name as a parameter
here and if I go back to my request now
go to details uh here in the name I am
going to select Max okay
and also in the response I am going to
verify uh whether it is Max or not okay
so there are two verifications now for
my response and also I am sending a
different value on the request okay
using the business parameter so let's
see if this works or not so let's go
ahead and run this now
okay so uh the test case has passed okay
uh it was able to send the request and
both verifications were successful the
status code was 200 okay and the name
was also matching which is now Max
instead of something else right
so now you can see that I can verify
correctly whether my request and
response are actually matching or they
have been scanned properly right because
we saw that previously uh it was not
scanned properly because my post request
had a different name and uh my response
had a different name right because it
was scanned from a previous execution so
uh even if you scan your API you should
not be sure that you are sending the
right details so that all the values
which you are going to send for a
request or the details which is required
to process that request it should be
configured okay and that configuration
value should go in your test case when
you are executing it and similarly uh
while you are receiving a response you
have to verify that the expected values
are present in your API response okay so
this is how you can create your test
cases in Tosca Commander by exporting it
from the API scan and also you can put
some verifications you can create
business parameters uh from your API
messages and then verify them
so next we are going to talk about how
we can actually use this or we can
buffer these values right the ID which
is coming back from the response because
we need this to verify our or to send
our get and delete request which
requires a path parameter which is the
ID right so in order to use this ID from
the response we need to store it
somewhere or we need to basically buffer
that value and once we buffer that value
then we can use that in our other
request so that is what we are going to
look in our next video where we use the
buffer method or the buffer action mode
to basically buffer different values
from the response and use it in other
get request where that ID or any other
value can be used by buffering those
okay
so that's all for this video hopefully
this was helpful uh in understanding how
you can work with API messages and then
export them back to your Tosca commander
and create test cases out of it right
we'll see lot more uh on this uh by
continuing in our next video so keep
watching and do tuning to our channel to
watch the next video on API testing
until then keep learning and don't
forget to subscribe to our Channel